Good morning, today is Tuesday, May 10th, 20th day of Omer, אסרו
חג Isru Chag of יום העצמאות. Yom Haatzmaut. We pick up on
דף Daf ס"ג... Samech Gimmel... what דף Daf are we?
ס"ג. Samech Gimmel. Thank you.
ס"ג, Samech Gimmel, but we pick up at the bottom of ס"ב
עמוד ב'. Samech Bet Amud Bet. And we are dealing with this
idea that our משנה Mishna says if a man says to a
woman, "I'm married to you after you get divorced" or "after your
husband dies, after I convert, you convert", it doesn't work. But the
גמרא Gemara deals with a case that maybe could work, maybe according
to everybody, a scenario in which something is בידו, B'yado, something that
the person can control. So it dealt not with a case of
קידושין Kidushin but a case of taking תרומה Terumah of stuff that's
growing from the ground, that is in his ability to pick the
fruit. Although by קידושין Kidushin it's more complicated, we gave an interesting
scenario, "I'll divorce you, I'm married to you already, now I'm married
to you and I'm married to you again after I divorce you".
So even though he could divorce her, somehow the whole thing is
not as much controllable by him because she has to agree to
being married. Anyway, so that wouldn't necessarily work. But the point is
that even though you can't be מקנה Makhne or do a קידושין
Kidushin or whatever if all the components aren't there, דבר שלא בא
לעולם, Davar Shelo Ba L'olam, if it's בידו B'yado it might be
enough that it is there in potential. We actually discussed interesting cases
about buying and selling futures, I guess selling futures, selling something you
don't have if that thing is readily available to purchase. From there
the גמרא Gemara focused on the position of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov where
even if it is not בידו, B'yado, but it's something that's going
to happen naturally, you know, standing grain that's going to ripen, and
he said that that could work. And that now moves us into
the area of positions that say you can do something for דבר
שלא בא לעולם, Davar Shelo Ba L'olam, because a lot of the
דבר שלא בא לעולםs Davar Shelo Ba L'olam are things that will
happen naturally. You know, the fruit will grow off of the tree
and so on. And it's really like we should sort of distinguish
between three categories. There's something that's not here that you can bring
about, that's בידו, B'yado, that you might say works even if normally
you cannot do something with a דבר שלא בא לעולם, Davar Shelo
Ba L'olam, but you can make that happen, okay. Then there are
things which will naturally happen if everything goes as planned and it's
expected that it will happen: the grain will ripen, the pregnant woman
will give birth and so on. Sadly, it doesn't always work out
that way, but that's seen as sort of natural, okay. That's, and
then there are things which are, you know, not likely, a lot
of obstacles or whatever, not predictable that will happen: that you'll be
freed from being a slave, that your husband will die, you know,
those types of things. Those are the extreme forms of דבר שלא
בא לעולם. Davar Shelo Ba L'olam. But what we were dealing with
yesterday was רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov who holds
a middle form of דבר שלא בא לעולם, Davar Shelo Ba L'olam,
things
that
will
happen
naturally and as anticipated. Now we pick up at the bottom of
the גמרא Gemara and it says the following: אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
four lines from the bottom, end of the line in ס"ב עמוד
ב'. Samech Bet Amud Bet. Said אביי: Abaye: רבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, ורבי, ve-Rabbi, these three
תנאים, Tana'im, כולהו סבירא להו, Kulu Sevira Lehu, all are of the
opinion אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. Adam Makhne Davar Shelo Ba
L'olam. A person can take possession of something or
can transfer ownership of something, can be מקנה, Makhne, can transfer ownership
of something or someone that has not yet come into the world.
Okay, אביי Abaye generally does this. אביי Abaye looks at different תנאים
Tana'im that have roughly the same type of a legal approach to
something and pulls them together and says they're all sort of of
a similar position. They're not identical, but they're of a similar
position, okay. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, what we
just said about the case of fruit that is not yet ripened.
So it's not בא לעולם Ba L'olam and you can't make it
happen, but hopefully it will happen. That's the most the easiest case
of דבר שלא בא לעולם. Davar Shelo Ba L'olam. רבי, Rabbi, how
'bout רבי? Rabbi? דתניא, De-Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, top
of ס"ג עמוד א': Samech Gimmel Amud Alef: לא תסגיר עבד אל
אדוניו, Lo Tashgir Eved el Adonav, you shall not hand over a
slave to his master. רבי אומר, Rabbi Omer, רבי Rabbi says בלוקח
עבד על מנת לשחררו הכתוב מדבר. Be-Lokeach Eved al Menat L'shachro ha-Katuv
medaber. What that means is that if somebody purchased a slave from
a non-Jew or from whomever and he stipulates that he will free
the slave, then then then we cannot and then he changes his
mind or whatever it is. We the בית דין, Beis Din, we
the community
can't return him to his master. You promised that you would free
him, we have to therefore protect and ensure his freedom. That's the
scenario. Now the גמרא Gemara wants to say, okay, what does that
have to do with us? So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי,
heichi dami, what's the case?
אמר רב דימי בר יצחק, Amar Rav Dimi bar Yitzchak, כגון דכתב
ליה לכשאקחך הרי עצמך קנויה לך מעכשיו, kegon de-chasav lei lech-she-ekkachecha harei
atzmecha k'nuya lach me-achshav, you are freed as of now. Okay, yourself
is owned by you, meaning you are freed as of now. I'm
going to get back to the word "as of now" in a
minute. Okay. Anyway, so what does that show you? It shows you
that he went ahead and he did the transaction of freeing the
slave before he owned the slave, before he was in a position
to do it. It also wasn't בידו, b'yado, the other person wasn't
necessarily going to sell him the slave—I mean, he might have said
he would, but he could not fully control it—and nevertheless that act
of freeing the slave works. Okay. And therefore, now how do we
know that's what רבי Rebbi is talking about? Because, you know, as
תוספות Tosafos says, if all the guy said is I promise I'm
going to free you, then it's hard to imagine that the תורה
Torah would have said, you know, do not return the slave to
the master. I mean, maybe it could have, but...
meaning he has to free, meaning this new guy has to free
him.
Yeah, the new guy, right, that it's basically sort of saying like
you made a promise. I mean, הלכה halacha normally does not see
promises—they're morally binding, but it does not really see them as legally
binding. Okay. So we understand that it could not just be a
promise; it has to have been something that actually took effect and
that therefore they're enforcing the actual freedom. Okay. So that's sort of
this, and it can't be that he just, you know, סתם stam
freed him. Why not? Because a master who frees his slave, he,
you know, and then he changed his
mind, because part of what sort of תוספות Tosafos points out is
the phrase is do not return a slave to the master. Then
he wouldn't be a slave; then it would be do not return
a freedman to the master, you know? So what sort of makes
him both a slave and it legally binding? So therefore that's going
to lead to constructing this scenario where, you know, he was sort
of purchased as a slave, but somehow because of this act that
he did, the slave should be free as a result.
Absolutely. Yeah. Is this the source of דבר שלא בא לעולם? davar
she-lo ba l'olam?
Right. So what אביי Abaye is sort of saying is like the
fact that רבי Rebbi is able to read the פסוק pasuk this
way, choosing to read the פסוק pasuk this way, shows that he
approaches the פסוק pasuk with the presumption that the whole transaction worked.
What?
What do we need the פסוק pasuk for?
That we as a community have a responsibility to protect the slave's
freedom. I mean, it's not to say that the act was binding.
לא תשיב, lo sashiv, don't return the slave to the master.
It's not for the... so what we're trying to say is this
works?
Well, you could read it this way: the תורה's Torah informing you
that this transaction works. No, no, no. The guy purchased the slave
and promised to free him. That works. That's... now the guy is,
the slave is freed. And what the תורה Torah is telling us:
do not return the slave to this second master, right, if the
master changes his mind.
Why is it not return? I mean, we're trying to use this
to prove that אדם אינו מקנה דבר שלא בא
לעולם?
adam eino makneh davar she-lo
ba l'olam?
No, אדם מקנה, adam makneh, and
that's why the תורה Torah has to tell you לא תשיב. lo
sashiv.
Right, exactly, exactly, exactly. So now, I understand, that's not our interest.
Now תוספות Tosafos raises an important question, which is the מעכשיו me-achshav
word. Because תוספות, Tosafos, I mean, two questions. Number one is if
you look at all the other cases of לא בא לעולם, lo
ba l'olam, they don't say מעכשיו. me-achshav. If anything, they say the
opposite, right? This will be תרומה terumah when it gets לכשיתלשו, lich-she-yitlashu,
when they get picked. Okay. And so number one is all the
other cases don't say מעכשיו. me-achshav. Number two is all the other
cases, logically, מעכשיו me-achshav doesn't work, right? I mean, this is the
question. It's what it means to say that you have enough of
the components that the transaction will be meaningful, but how could it
take effect at this stage when, you know, when he's not your
slave, or when this woman is already married, still married to this
other guy, right? Right. Like obviously what it means is the act
works, it works enough so that it will take effect when the
components come, you know, when the necessary pieces fall into place. So
תוספות Tosafos basically has a long תוספות Tosafos figuring out what מעכשיו
me-achshav means. And one level he says it really doesn't mean like
anything—I mean, you know, how to explain it? Like why it said.
But the other thing that he, you know, it's just to clarify
what רבי Rebbi was getting at, but that it really doesn't have
any legal meaning. The other thing תוספות Tosafos says is maybe the
purpose of מעכשיו, me-achshav, you remember the whole discussion we had that
if you do an act that takes effect later, the act still
has to be somewhat in position, like the remnant of the act,
of the transaction, still has to be present when it takes effect?
So if I say, for example, you know, take this, what do
you call it, this recorder, thank you, and you'll own it in
30 days, then 30 days from now this recorder might have to
still be to some degree under your control. If it was in
the middle of the street, maybe you wouldn't own it because there's
nothing that remains of that transaction that we did. So תוספות Tosafos
says
because... So תוספות Tosafos says yeah, but by the case of a
slave when you give him a שטר shtar because you have to
free a slave with a writ, with a שטר, shtar, so what
would happen if the שטר shtar was torn or lost, would it
still work? So תוספות Tosafos says maybe the only purpose of the
point of the word מעכשיו me'achshav is not to make it happen
now. There was no way it could happen now because you don't
have the right components in place now, but מעכשיו me'achshav gives the
act enough strength, enough seriousness, that it allows it to work even
if there's no remnant of the act later. So even if the
שטר shtar gets torn up, because you said, you know, מעכשיו me'achshav
sort of means it'll be as if it is from now. Okay,
it doesn't really take place now, but because you said as of
now, that means that there doesn't have to be any remnant of
the קנין. kinyan. Yes, but besides as soon as possible, what it
means is since now we have all of the pieces of the
act present, well we don't have the fact that you're not mine,
but we have the actual transaction present, then then we don't need
any element of that transaction later.
You have to have at least written the שטר shtar then, right?
Oh of course, no you totally have to give the שטר. shtar.
The whole point of דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba l'olam
is that you give the שטר shtar now to this slave who
you don't own. I mean that's the irony. It's like you give
the ring to the woman who's still married to another man and
it takes effect when she gets divorced. You give the שטר shtar
to a slave owned by another man and it takes effect once
he gets free. But if you didn't say מעכשיו, me'achshav, you just
said words, you just made a promise. If you didn't say מעכשיו,
me'achshav, he'd still have to be holding onto the שטר. shtar. Okay,
but anyway the upshot of all of this is that דבר שלא
בא לעולם davar shelo ba l'olam only works when the necessary pieces
fall into place, but the transaction is done now.
Rabbi, did you yesterday talk about the phrase in the
משנה mishnah הוקר וברא?
hukar u'bara? הוקר וברא Hukar u'bara wasn't in the משנה, mishnah, got
sort of conflated in or like, you know, what do you call
it, glossed in because of the discussion in the גמרא, gemara, but
that was discussed at the end of yesterday's דף. daf. Yeah, that
הוקר וברא hukar u'bara whatever, yes. I don't want to go back
to that. Yeah, that was the end of yesterday's דף. daf. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara says like this. Okay, so that's רבי. Rebbi.
רבי מאיר דתניא, Rabbi Meir d'tanya, how about רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is usually the classic תנא tanna that is
identified with דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar shelo ba l'olam. We taught
in a ברייתא braisa האומר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שאתגייר
לאחר שתתגיירי לאחר שאשתחרר לאחר שתשתחררי ha'omer l'isha harey at mekudeshes li
l'achar she'isgayer l'achar she'tisgayri l'achar she'ishtachrer l'achar she'tishtachrari after I get converted,
you convert, I get freed, you get freed, certainly not בידו, b'yado,
certainly not something that necessarily would naturally happen that a slave would
be freed. Okay, so this is the extreme cases. לאחר שימות בעליך
לאחר שתמות אחותיך, l'achar sheyamus ba'aleich l'achar shetamus achoseich, your husband dies,
your sister dies, okay, if he had been once been married to
the sister. לאחר שיחלוץ ליבמיך l'achar sheyachalotz l'yevameich after your brother-in-law does
חליצה, chalitzah, that would presume that you cannot do קידושין kidushin with
a woman who needs to have חליצה chalitzah done, which is not
the way we פסקן. pasken. אינה מקודשת, eina mekudeshes, doesn't work. רבי
מאיר אומר מקודשת, Rabbi Meir omer mekudeshes, it works. So there you
go, דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba l'olam in some of
these, this is the most extreme forms of it. Not only is
it extreme because you don't know it'll come about and you can't
actually anticipate it will come about, but I've got to tell you,
I for one can still never understand that a non-Jew can say
do a transaction that is only a קידושין kidushin is only an
institution that exists for Jews, right? It's not like purchasing property that
exists for Jews and non-Jews but maybe we have different ways of
doing it. Okay, the whole institution of קידושין, kidushin, I mean yes,
הלכה halacha recognizes marriage for non-Jews but it's a different
institution, right? It's basically נישואין nisuin or whatever. So anyway, that you
can do this whole act and you're not even a legal participant.
I mean I guess it's similar to the guy who's marrying off
the, marrying the fetus, and the fetus isn't alive yet, but what,
yeah exactly, exactly, robbing the cradle. Anyway, but somehow the ability that
a person is an actor in a legal transaction, not just they
don't have the components in place, the woman is still a married
woman, you know, but not even like a legal entity, you know,
to me it's just like mind-blowing that that can work, דבר שלא
בא לעולם. davar shelo ba l'olam. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says. Okay, רבי יוחנן הסנדלר אומר אינה מקודשת. Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar omer
eina mekudeshes. רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar
repeats the position of the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, it does not
work. ורבי יהודה הנשיא אומר מקודשת. Ve'Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi omer mekudeshes. רבי
יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi
actually agrees with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and says it does work
even though it's שלא בא לעולם. shelo ba l'olam. ומה טעם אמרו
אינה מקודשת? Uma ta'am amru eina mekudeshes? But the rabbis said we
won't recognize the קידושין. kidushin. So here you basically have an idea
of like אפקינהו רבנן לקידושין. afkinhu rabanan l'kidushin. Technically she's married but
in some of these cases, we'll see in two of these cases,
the rabbis refuse to recognize the קידושין. kidushin. Why do they refuse
to recognize the קידושין? kidushin? משום איבה mishum eivah because of hatred.
What is the איבה eivah case? So רש"י Rashi explains the איבה
eivah case is: You're married to me on the condition that your
husband dies. You're married to me on the condition that your sister
dies. So we could not recognize that. That would have everybody waiting.
around right and then the husband mysteriously dies. Okay so we cannot
recognize that that is too much creates way too much tension and
so you know and and and problems within society. Those cannot be
recognized.
Wait so the non-Jewish case is fine?
The non-Jewish case is fine. In principle רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi totally agrees with רבי, Rabbi, just a little social policy you
know that we have to we have to override it in two
cases. So the גמרא Gemara says ונחשוב נמי רבי u'nechshov nami Rabbi
oh, so the גמרא Gemara says okay so that was your proof
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is in the list, he's really the
top of the list. So the גמרא Gemara says ונחשוב נמי רבי
יהודה הנשיא? u'nechshov nami Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi? Oh but רבי יהודה הנשיא
Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi agrees with רבי Rabbi what with רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, include him in your list. No, היינו רבי היינו רבי יהודה
הנשיא hainu Rabbi hainu Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi because we already quoted רבי
Rabbi before by the case of the slaves. So you see, it
could be otherwise. I know this is a much better one, go
go because it now gives us different applications of it, so it's
a little more interesting. Okay, ונחשוב נמי רבי עקיבא. u'nechshov nami Rabbi
Akiva. Oh you can add רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva to your list.
How do you know? דתניא de'tanya we taught a ברייתא: baraita: קונם
שאני עושה לפיך. konam she'ani oseh le'picha. A woman says to her
husband קונם, konam, which basically means it's like הקדש, hekdesh, makes it
אסור בנדר assur be'neder anything that I produce. So this is a
woman and her labor is the husband has rights to her labor
based on the laws of the כתובה, ketubah, and she says anything
that I produce you know through the labor of my hands you
know that should be אסור assur to you as a קונם, konam,
like as a נדר, neder, like הקדש, hekdesh, okay, לפיך le'picha you
won't be you know אסור assur to you to be eaten. All
right. And any benefit.
Right, or you can't get any benefit from anything I do and
so on. רבי עקיבא אומר יפר. Rabbi Akiva omer yafer. He does
not have to annul it. The husband can annul, but here he
doesn't have to annul because he owns, see he has rights to
this, right? Her labor is owned by him, so she's not in
a position to annul it. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no he
has to to what? He's not—he's not—right, he's not in a position
to forbid it. Thank you. He doesn't need to annul it because
she's not in a position to forbid it. It's not hers to
forbid. רבי עקיבא אומר יפר. Rabbi Akiva omer yafer. No no no
he still he should annul it, שמא תעדיף עליו יותר מן הראוי
לו shema ta'adifa alav yoter min ha'ra'uy lo because maybe she will
produce more than he is obligated to him. Right? The כתובה ketubah
demands that she does a certain amount of labor. If she does
more than that labor, she's entitled to keep it to herself. So
therefore if he forbids everything she produces, it might include the extra
that actually she does own and therefore he should annul. Okay because
some of that could be forbidden. Now by the way תוספות tosafot
asks an interesting question: why isn't he in a position to annul?
He's only in a position to annul things that impact their relationship,
but if she's entitled to keep the extra that's her own property
and she doesn't have an obligation to give it to him, why
can't she she do that? That's not something that's about their relationship.
So תוספות tosafot says there is no way you can exactly figure
out did I do a couple of pennies extra you know more
or less? So the presence of that נדר neder gets in the
way of him benefiting even from the stuff that he is entitled
to, right? Because you never exactly know was this the extra or
not the extra. Anyway that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. So
the גמרא Gemara says now how can she forbid it with a
נדר? neder? It doesn't exist yet. How can you make something אסור
assur with a נדר neder that doesn't yet exist? Okay so the
גמרא Gemara that seems like a דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar she'lo
ba l'olam. Now that's a world of נדרים nedarim where you can
sort of create reality so who knows maybe you have more latitude
there, but the גמרא Gemara anyway gets out of it. The גמרא
Gemara says הא איתמר עלה אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע ha
itmar alah amar Rav Huna breih de'Rav Yehoshua this is not that
she makes the food forbidden and the food doesn't exist yet, but
באומרת יקדשו ידי לעושיהן. b'omeres yikdeshu yadai l'oseihen. She says may my
hands be forbidden, you know, the נדר neder is in a way
חל chal on her hands, the you know the hands in regards
to what they produce, meaning not that she can't—the hands themselves like
he can't touch her hands. Okay this is not הלכה halakhah but
you know, it's like when you can own a tree for its
fruit and you can own somebody's hand for their labor. So but
the hands for what they will produce are אסור בנדר. assur be'neder.
Okay וידים איתנהו בעולם ve'yadayim itnhu b'olam and the hands are in
the world so therefore it's not a דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar
she'lo ba l'olam.
It's like saying a נדר neder on bananas but the bananas haven't
started to exist yet. Right, right. That's a נדר neder either because
there's—נדר neder
on
bananas—well that's interesting.
That's another interesting point that's true like if you say אסור assur
to me כל פירות שבעולם, kol peirot she'ba'olam, what about the פירות
peirot that don't exist yet where that's like a class of things?
It's an interesting question, right? I don't remember at all נדרים nedarim
discussing that when you sort of make for yourself forbidden a whole
class of objects, not a concrete one, would that include things that
have not yet—don't yet exist? But if you say the bananas of
this—but if you say the bananas of this tree are forbidden to
me and the bananas haven't grown yet, I mean that's a good
parallel, then if you say you can't do דבר שלא בא לעולם
davar she'lo ba l'olam that נדר neder wouldn't work. But if you
said אסור assur to me this tree
לבננותיו, le'bananotav,
so in that case it would work because the נדר neder would
be on the tree for that capacity or whatever that it will
produce its bananas.
Exactly, exactly, that would be the same.
Plus the question of ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי יהודה הנשיא.
Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi.
Right, like
didn't the גמרא Gemara know that it was רבי? Rebbi? Yeah, I
don't know, I don't know, like what was even the הוה אמינא?
hava amina? Right, I have no idea. Like any, you know, hopefully
any child will say, what do you mean, that's רבי, Rebbi, you
just said רבי? Rebbi? Yeah, I don't know what the הוה אמינא
hava amina was. Okay, anyway. Okay, האומר לאשה, Ha'omer l'isha, next משנה.
mishna. So that was the end of marrying a woman who's still
not a or the guy is not yet Jewish, the woman isn't
Jewish, she's still married, whatever. The basic משנה mishna is you can't
do דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, it does not
work. Next משנה. mishna. האומר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי על מנת
שאדבר עליך לשלטון. Ha'omer l'isha harei at mekudeshet li al mnat she'adaber
alayich lashilton. You are married to me on the condition that I
put in a good word for you with, you know, with the
governor, with the mayor. Okay. ואעשה עמך כפועל. v'e'eseh imach k'poel.
So or I will, I'll do some day labor for you, I'll
mow your lawn on the condition that I'll speak to the mayor
for you, I'll mow your lawn. דיבר עליה לשלטון. Diber aleha lashilton.
If he went and did what he promised, he said something to
the mayor on her behalf. או עשה עמה כפועל. o asah imah
k'poel. Or he mowed her lawn. מקודשת, Mekudeshet, it works. ואם לאו
אינה מקודשת, v'im lav einah mekudeshet, this does not work. Now the
point is this all seems pretty obvious. So let's take a look.
So אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Resh Lakish. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
says והוא שנתן לה שוה פרוטה. v'hu she'natan lah shaveh pruta. He
is not marrying her with the value of that service, right? It's
like every other משנה. mishna. He gives her the ring and he
says on the condition that I do X. So even though here
the X is a type of a service that has a market
value, he's not marrying her with the service, he's marrying her with
the ring, okay, and he's doing the service and it's on the
condition that he does the service.
Okay? The first example is a service, a little different, don't you
think?
No, what are you talking about? Somebody putting in a good word
with you with a politician.
No, if I mow your lawn, the grass is cut.
Yeah, you know, you know how I know it's a service? 'Cause
lobbyists make millions of dollars to do exactly that. Of course it's
a service. Speaking to a... it doesn't necessarily... whether it actually leads
to the desired result does not mean that it's not something that
people pay and they pay handsomely for for people to actually petition
on their behalf, you know, with a politician and so on.
Okay, so the only thing that's being paid for is my putting
in that word. After that, whether it goes anywhere or not, that's
not my problem.
Exactly. But you performed a very powerful service. You put in a
good word for somebody. That's something that you can charge really good
money for. Now רש"י Rashi says if you've already given the ring
and this is just a condition—I'm just saying ring 'cause I want
to make it contemporary obviously. If you've already given the פרוטה pruta
and this is just a condition, what's the חידוש chiddush of the
משנה? mishna? So רש"י Rashi says according to this read, the חידוש
chiddush of the משנה mishna is exactly that point, that you have
to give the ring, that this works as a תנאי, tnai, as
a condition.
Wait, the ring wasn't mentioned in the משנה? mishna?
Yeah, well, it wasn't mentioned anywhere else. הרי את מקודשת לי על
מנת שבעליך ימות, Harei at mekudeshet li al mnat she'ba'alech yamut, הרי
את מקודשת לי על מנת שאני נותן לך מאתיים זוז. harei at
mekudeshet li al mnat she'ani noten lach matayim zuz. Right? Why? Because
it's obvious, you did the act of קידושין kiddushin and all the
משנה's mishna talking about are conditions that you've added to the act.
So according—it's a completely consistent read with everything else and the חידוש
chiddush is that you can't marry her with the service, the service
can only function as a תנאי, tnai, as a condition. Now why
can't you marry her with the service? We'll see, 'cause you would
think why not? It's something of value. Okay, but that's one read,
that the service only can work as a condition, it cannot work
as the way in which you marry her. Yes?
Yeah, I was going to bring up there's a question of the
difference between tangible and intangible property and חז"ל Chazal is not all
that comfortable...
Yes, but you can marry a woman with things of value. On
the... the value that I will be מוחל mochel your debt, the
value that I will, you know, all those other types of things.
So let's take a look. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says like
all the other משניות, mishnayot, you've given the... you did the act
of קידושין, kiddushin, you gave her the פרוטה, pruta, you gave her
the ring, and this is just a condition. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says ובשכר לא? u'vischar lo? Are you telling me you can't
marry her with the with the like the the value of the
fee for this service? והתניא, ve'hatanya, we turn a ברייתא. braita. בשכר
שהרכבתיך על
החמור, Bischar she'hirkavtich al hachamor, a man says to a woman, you
know, I will marry you on the... because of... with the... with
the fee for that I... that I rode you on the, you
know, that I gave you a donkey ride. או שהושבתיך בקרון o
she'hoshavtich b'karon או
בספינה, o bisafina, or that, you know, I put you in the
wagon or in the or in the boat, you know, that I
gave you a ferry ride. אינה מקודשת, Eina mekudeshet, that doesn't work
because he already did it in the past and therefore she just
owes him money. So that's the case of מקדש במלוה, mekadesh b'milveh,
right? If he's basically saying with the money... he's not saying with
the value of my being waiving what you owe me, but actually
with the money itself. But that's מלוה, milveh, that the money doesn't
exist, the fee is already... the act of service has already taken
place. Okay, now, but if he says
בשכר שאושיביך על החמור, bischar she'oshivich al hachamor, שאושיביך בקרון או בספינה,
she'oshivich b'karon o bisafina, with the fee for that I will give
you... a donkey ride or a boat ride, מקודשת, mekudeshet, then he
does the service, it's not yet a debt, she doesn't it didn't
happen already, she doesn't owe him any money, he does a service
for her and the value of this service, that will be the
פרוטה prutah that you will receive. Okay, I'm going to give you
something. I'm going to give you a free ride, right? Give you
a, so that's something I gave you. If I gave you a
plane ticket, that's worth a lot of money. So if I comped
you for the plane flight, right? And I gave you a free
ride, I gave you something of great value. That works. So you
see you can do it with the fee for with the fee
for a service. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי תימא הכא נמי
בדיהבה לה שוה פרוטה. vechi teima hacha nami bedeyahavlah shaveh prutah. Oh
wait, maybe those cases of the donkey ride etc. is when he
gave her a ring. No, השתא בשכר קאמר. hashta bisechar ka'amar. It's
clear enough. You're saying I am marrying you with the fee. Okay,
and it's not על מנת, al menat, it's with the fee. ותניא,
vetanya, it's in another ברייתא: braita: שבי עמי בצוותא, shevi imi bitzavta,
if a woman says to
a man, here, sit next to me, keep me company, ואקדש לך,
ve'ekadesh lach, and I'll and
I'll marry you, I'll agree to marry
you with the value of that, of that you're keeping me company.
שחוק לפני sechok lefanai or do some type of a stand-up comedy
routine. רקוד לפני, rekod lefanai, do a dance in front of me.
עשה כדמות הזה, aseh kidmus hazeh, make like this form, like a
build like I think it's a building, or כדמות, kidmus, maybe some
structure. But there might be a more interesting read of that. Does
Steinzaltz say anything interesting about עשה כדמות הזה? aseh kidmus hazeh? Do
this jigsaw. Yeah, I'm wondering because the other things are some type
of a demonstration or service. דמות dmus is like building something. Anyway,
you'll see if Steinzaltz says anything. לעשות? la'asot? What? Make an edifice?
Yeah, anyway, but it doesn't like exactly fit the theme. Anyway, in
all those cases, שמין, shamin, you assess the value. אם יש בו
שוה פרוטה, im yesh bo shaveh prutah, if that was a type
of a thing that people would normally pay for...
a dollar, the guy doing that on the subway.
Right, exactly. Pay the guy a quarter to do a little dance,
entertain you. Okay. Twenty bucks for the, what's it called, the cover
charge to go see a comedy routine. Okay. Then מקודשת. mekudeshet. ואם
לאו אינה מקודשת, ve'im lav einah mekudeshet, and if not, not. So
you see you do a service and for the for the value
of the service you can that can count as the money for
קידושין. kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי תימא הכא נמי בדיהבה
לה שוה פרוטה, vechi teima hacha nami bedeyahavlah shaveh prutah, maybe you're
also you gave a ring. No, השתא שמינהו קאמר, hashta shaminahu ka'amar,
then why would it say you assess the value? Clearly in all
these cases you are marrying the woman with the value of the
service. So the גמרא Gemara says, תיובתא דריש לקיש, tiyuvta deResh Lakish,
isn't that a contradiction to ריש לקיש? Resh Lakish? Because ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish is implying that it only works as a condition, you
can't actually marry the woman with the service of speaking to the
mayor. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. אמר לך ריש לקיש, amar
lach Resh Lakish, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish would say back to you,
האי תנא ברא, hai tanna bara, the תנא tanna of all those
ברייתות, braitot, that outside תנא, tanna, סבר אינה לשכירות אלא לבסוף. savar
einah lisechirut ela levasof. Yes, feels that it can work by the
service because feels that the sort of the
money owed for a service only comes at the end of the
service. ותנא דידן, vetanna didan, our תנא tanna that only allows it
to work as a condition but not as the money for קידושין,
kiddushin, סבר ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף, savar yeshnah lisechirut mitechilah ve'ad
sof, that the שכירות sechirut starts from beginning to end. What does
that mean? It means you're going ahead and you're doing the service
for me, right? You're mowing my lawn. Is it when you're done
I owe you twenty dollars, or is it for every blade of
grass I owe you a tenth of a penny? Okay. So that's
the question. And when it all finishes, then it's okay, but every
single little blade is increasing my debt, a tiny
tiny infinitesimal amount. Okay. So if you say that's אינה לשכירות אלא
לבסוף, einah lisechirut ela levasof, when you're done I owe you twenty
dollars. Okay. Or no, ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף yeshnah lisechirut mitechilah
ve'ad sof is I owe you every little bit. I guess an
interesting נפקא מינא nafka mina is if I mowed a quarter of
the lawn, do you owe me a quarter? Ha! That's a good
point. Anyway, so I wonder if
the גמרא Gemara ever deals with that. I'd have to see
that. Anyway, so in that case, if I owe you twenty dollars
at the end, here I am, I'm mowing your lawn. Right now,
I've done a service that you don't owe me anything. When I'm
done, it's like a there's a twenty dollar service here that you
would owe me twenty dollars and I basically say, no, this service
is a gift. I have given you now a twenty dollar gift.
Okay. Whereas if I'm mowing the lawn and then what I'm really
saying is every every like one hundredth of a penny, I'm giving
to you. I'm giving you this blade of grass, I'm giving you
that blade of grass. Okay.
And therefore, I'm giving you a lot of partial פרוטות, prutot, but
I've never given you a פרוטה. prutah. Okay. So that's the difference.
No, in the end, I first I gave her a tenth of
a פרוטה, prutah, I can't marry her with that, then I gave
her another tenth of a פרוטה, prutah, I can't marry her with
that. Now, I guess it does raise an interesting question, which is
if I say I'm going to marry you with a פרוטה prutah
and I give it to her in little tenths of a פרוטות
prutot down payments, right? So that's interesting. Like why can't you say
that the cumulative amount... but I think the reason is because there,
since it didn't work the first tenth of a פרוטה, prutah, it
becomes like a
debt and... Because it's not actually concrete money. It was concrete money
in my hand, at the end of the day I've got a
פרוטה Prutah in my hand, but here it's abstract. So it's either
a מלווה Milveh or it's the כסף קידושין. Kessef kiddushin. That's right.
The reason why you can't be מקדש Mekadesh with מלווה Milveh is
because it's not yours, it's hers.
It's no longer your money that you're giving her. Right. So I
understand the question, but that's the basic idea. So anyway, all these
cases which says you can be מקדש Mekadesh with a service feels
that the whole value comes at the end, and then you're giving
her something at the end that's worth a פרוטה. Prutah. Our משנה
Mishna which only has it as a תנאי, Tnai, feels that the
value, the sort of debt or you know what's being given is
measured in every second, and therefore you're never giving a פרוטה. Prutah.
So then the גמרא Gemara says like this, one minute. ומאי דוחקיה
דריש לקיש דאוקמה למתניתין בישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף. U'mai duhkheih d'Resh
Lakish d'ukma l'matnisin b'yeshna l'skhirut mitkhilah v'ad sof. What pushed Resh Lakish
to interpret our משנה Mishna that way? That, you know, every tiny
little hundredth of a penny is getting given, you know, and the
whole thing is a process that begins from beginning to end and
it doesn't work as כסף קידושין. Kessef kiddushin. And בדיעבד bdieved he
wants to say, but it's talking that you gave her a ring
and this is all a תנאי. Tnai. Why not say the משנה
Mishna is that this was the כסף קידושין? Kessef kiddushin? So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא מתניתין קשיא ליה. Amar Rava matnisin kashya
lei. He's just doing, he was bothered by the language of the
משנה. Mishna. He was just doing a very reasonable read of the
פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishna.
מאי איריא דתני על מנת, Mai irya d'tani al m'nat, why does
the משנה Mishna say you're married me on the condition that I
speak to the mayor? ניתיני בשכר, Nisni b'skhar, say you're married to
me with the value of my speaking to the mayor, with the
fee that normally I would charge to speak to the mayor for
you. אלא שמע מינה כל על מנת היכא דיהב לה הוא. Ella
shema mina kol al m'nat heikha d'yehav lah hu. Every time the
משניות mishnayot before said על מנת, Al m'nat, means you gave her
the ring and you made an external condition. So that was true
of all the previous משניות, mishnayot, on the condition that your sister
dies or on the condition that I give you two hundred dollars.
It's true of this משנה. Mishna. The act of קידושין Kiddushin was
done and this is an independent קידושין. Kiddushin. If you wanted to
say that this was the value with which you were marrying with,
this was the fee that was being given, then the משנה Mishna
should have been formulated otherwise. And it's totally right, that is completely
פשט pshat of the משנה, Mishna, which is interesting. Right, sometimes an
אמורא Amora approaches with a halakhic position and is trying to read
the halakhic position into the משנה. Mishna. Here Resh Lakish is saying,
I don't even know, you know, like it's irrelevant to me right
now how we פסקן, pasken, ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף yeshna l'skhirut
mitkhilah v'ad sof or not. Clearly it's a debate, clearly there are
plenty of ברייתות Braitot that feel that you can marry with the
fee and so on. I'm not taking any halakhic position on that
matter. I'm just saying that's not what's going on in our משנה.
Mishna. Yes, Charlie.
Is there such a thing as a halakhic obligation for less than
a פרוטה? Prutah?
Yeah, I mean that's an interesting question. Normally less than a פרוטה
Prutah is not seen as money, but whether that means that it's
not, you know, you can't sue for it or whether it means
like, you know, that a debt doesn't really exist? I mean for
example, think about the idea of a bank, right, where a bank
basically, you know, your interest is accruing in tiny little, that's a
real ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshna l'skhirut mitkhilah v'ad sof, right?
So and every tiny little increment adds up to a lot of
money. Well, not now anyway, but used to be.
Financial scandals where people took the...
I know the round up, I know about that. Anyway. But yeah,
but so, but it is a good point that normally we don't
treat it that way but I think that means more to sue
for it in court. But, you know, as opposed to... All right,
but there is a good question about that. All right, let's look
at the next משנה. Mishna. על מנת שירצה אבא, Al m'nat she'yirtzeh
Abba, שירצה אבא, she'yirtzeh Abba, on the condition that Dad agrees to
this, your Dad presumably agrees to our marriage. Okay. The woman's... the
woman's Dad. רצה אבא מקודשת, Ratza Abba mekudeshet, if the father agrees
she's... By the way, I should mention in the previous ברייתא Braita
quoted on where the woman says if you sit next to me
and keep me company then I'll be married to you with that,
it's very interesting in terms of discussions earlier about נתן הוא ואמר
היא natan hu v'amar hi about the woman having a speaking role
in the transaction. Because here she actually initiated it, she said I
will be married to you if you do this, it never had
him saying הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li. Right? It
could be that it was followed with that. But that was actually
quite interesting where she says, right, remember that case where it says
שב עמי בצוותא ואקדש לך shev imi b'tsavta v'ekadesh lakh or לך.
lekha. Okay? So actually it had the woman doing the whole initiating,
speaking, and even the קידושין kiddushin language. Anyway, back to our משנה.
Mishna. On the condition that Dad agrees. רצה אבא מקודשת, Ratza Abba
mekudeshet, if the father agrees she's married. ואם לאו אינה מקודשת, V'im
lav eina mekudeshet, and if not she's not married. Now, מת האב,
met ha'Ab, if the father died, הרי זו מקודשת, harei zu mekudeshet,
she's married. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to say, what do you
mean? He didn't agree. So does agree mean not object? Because if
he died then he never objected. All right. מת הבן, Met ha'ben,
now let's say the son... So now oh, it's now actually it's
clear that the אב Ab means my father, the groom's father. Okay.
So the groom said, my father agrees, okay, and then the groom
dies. Now, is this girl an אלמנה almanah or is she never
married? She'd much better off to be never married than to be
an אלמנה. almanah. Okay, so... In this case you want the קידושין
kiddushin not to take place, so what you do is מלמדין את
האב לומר שאינו רוצה, melamdin et ha'av lomar she'eino rotze, then you
instruct the father and say, look,
say you didn't approve of the marriage and then this girl won't
be an אלמנה almanah because there's nothing to be gained right now,
the groom is dead.
All right, let's pick up this last case where the father hasn't
expressed one way or the other.
Right, which is exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to try
to figure out, like what's the key moment? Is it express acceptance,
express rejection, not say anything? So let's see the גמרא. Gemara.
This is a little nine-year-old girl saying.
No, they could be two adults.
So the father... in other words she's bringing the father into the
condition.
Or he's bringing it in. The groom's father. He's bringing it in.
Okay. על מנת שירצה אבא. al mnat she'yirtze abba. What does it
mean on the condition that he is okay with
this, agrees? אילימא דאמר אבא אין, eileima d'amar abba in, he has
to actually verbally affirm that he's okay with
it. סיפא, seifa, let's look at the middle case. מת האב הרי
זו מקודשת, met ha'av harei zu mekudeshet, if he dies she's married.
והא לא אמר אין, ve'ha lo amar in, presumably it means he
died before doing anything. So right, that's the חידוש chiddush of the
משנה. Mishnah. So how could he be married? He never said he
was okay with it. אלא, ella, it implies that what does it
mean as long as dad is okay with it? It means על
מנת שישתוק אבא, al mnat she'yishtok abba, that he's silent, that he
doesn't object. Okay, now so he died, so he never objected. Perfect.
Okay. סיפא, seifa, so let's look at the end now. מת הבן
מלמדין את האב לומר שאינו רוצה. met haben melamdin et ha'av lomar
she'eino rotze. If the son dies you teach the father to say
he doesn't want it, which means that presumably now the גמרא Gemara
here like focuses in on the idea it says like this, here's
the dad okay, and he hears that his son died, okay,
מת הבן. met haben. He just hears that his son died. So
then if it's מלמדין אותו, melamdin oto, if this is a timeline,
okay, so he heard his son died and then we go in
and we jump in and we're מלמדין אותו, melamdin oto, we give
him instruction at that moment in time. Before we give him instruction
and after he hears that his son's died, presumably he's not he
doesn't know what to do, he might not even know that the
whole condition well whatever. So this is a period of he's being
silent, okay, there's שתיקה. shtikah. That's how the גמרא Gemara imagines what's
being described in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, he heard that his son
died, we will now teach him, we didn't teach him before he
heard his son died. Presumably there was a certain moment in time
that passed, okay, so there was a period of שתיקה. shtikah. So
if it means that the dad and presumably he also
knew of the whole condition, right, he also knew about the fact
that the son had married this woman on blah blah blah, he
had an opportunity to either say yes or no. That's how the
גמרא Gemara imagines it. You don't have to say that, you could
say we're מלמדין אותו, melamdin oto, we also inform him about the
whole reality. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara imagines that that's the scenario.
So for that case the point is is that if it says
on the on the condition that he's silent, so if silence means
silent as soon as he hears, then he already was
silent. But of course there could be silence could mean something else.
Silence could mean that he like doesn't object, it doesn't mean that
there's one second to make the decision. Okay, let's take a look.
So if it means silence and that makes the marriage binding, סיפא,
seifa, let's look at the end. And therefore if he dies he
was silent, right? So that would work. But let's look at the
end. מת הבן מלמדין את האב לומר שאינו רוצה. met haben melamdin
et ha'av lomar she'eino rotze. אמאי והא שתיק? amai ve'ha shtik? There
was a moment of silence. Why do you have to how does
saying אינו רוצה eino rotze work? By being silent here he already
established the קידושין. kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says, well minute, there's
an obvious answer, so let's let the גמרא Gemara say it. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר לה על מנת שלא ימחה אבא.
ella amar lah al mnat shelo yimche abba. No, no, no, silence
does not mean a moment of
silence. What makes the קידושין kiddushin that'll have a moment of silence?
A moment of silence once you find out makes the קידושין kiddushin
binding. It means as long as you don't object. Okay, so let's
see how the משנה Mishnah would play out. Okay, so the father
hears, if he's רוצה, rotze, which means by his silent he is
somehow implicit,
if
he verbally objects, doesn't work. If he verbally says fine it's great
I love it good nice young girl, okay, then then it works,
it's binding. Okay, what if he's silent and he hasn't responded yet?
Presumably in that case until he either verbally objects or verbally accepts
it it's unclear what the right it's up in the air. Okay,
but if he verbally but if he verbally objects then it's no
good. Now if he dies, so he never objected. So he never
objected, we're good. Okay. If he, the son dies, he still, so
his silence still doesn't mean anything. Okay. So it's still open what
he can do. So we tell him at that stage object and
it'll stop it from taking effect. All right? Everything works.
Isn't it a clear שתיקה כהודאה דמיא, shtika kehoda'a damya, no?
Yeah, but the גמרא Gemara wants to sort of say that if
it's only a moment of שתיקה shtika then it doesn't parse in
the משנה. mishna.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says so the גמרא's Gemara got a
problem though with this. I think that the משנה mishna reads this
way, but here's what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay. רישא בחדא טעמא וסיפא בחדא טעמא? Reisha bechada ta'ama useifa bechada
ta'ama? How can the beginning be in one scenario and the end
be in another scenario? Now what's the beginning scenario of the רישא?
reisha? So Dov was bothered by the fact that the way I
spelled it out is that if he actively says yes, then he
can't object after. If he actively objects, then again, if it's silent
it leaves it open-ended. And Dov was saying how can you leave
it indefinitely open-ended? But the גמרא Gemara has even a stranger read
of the משנה, mishna, at least the way רש״י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot both understand what's bothering the גמרא. Gemara. And if you framed
it as on the condition that he doesn't object, he can always
object even after he accepted, right, which is like crazy. He says
great, I love it whatever. And then a year from now he
says you know what I object. Well, it was only on the
condition that he didn't object, so eventually he objects. Right? It's a
bit crazy, you would think that once you accept you lose your
right to object. So therefore the גמרא Gemara says the משנה, mishna,
the רישא reisha of the משנה mishna doesn't make sense. How's the
רישא reisha of the משנה mishna when it says if he wants
she's מקודשת, mekudeshet, how is that true? As if the real condition
is as long as he doesn't object, she's never definitely מקודשת. mekudeshet.
He always can potentially object even after he verbally accepts. Okay. So
the גמרא, Gemara, if you're confused don't worry.
No, I'm not confused, it's just
it's bizarre.
It's completely bizarre that the גמרא Gemara thinks that if you formulate
something as on the condition you don't object, that you could verbally
affirm it and then say but eventually I'll object. Right. Anyway. So
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says so the רישא reisha has to
mean that you are silent. The סיפא seifa means you don't object.
So the גמרא Gemara says how could that be? גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רבי ינאי אין, Amar Rav Yannai in, yes, it's true. The
beginning means that it can't be that you have an indefinite period
to object. So the beginning is that as long as you're silent
it's okay, if you're not silent it's no good. And the סיפא
seifa is about actively objecting. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ריש
לקיש שמע מינה דרבי ינאי, Amar Resh Lakish shema mina deRav Yannai,
the fact that Rav Yannai was willing to say that the beginning
and end of the משנה mishna are about different circumstances, we hear
from him his a methodological point. That דדחקינן ומוקמינן מתניתין בתרי טעמי
ואליבא דחד תנא, dachtinan umokminan matnitin bitrei ta'amei ve'aliba dechad tana,
we'd rather have the משנה mishna be a single opinion of one
תנא tana even if it forces us saying that the first case
is different conditions than the end cases, the first case it basically
means on the condition that you're silent, and the end case means
on the condition that you don't object, we'd rather say that, ולא
מוקמינן בתרי תנאי תנאי ובחד טעמא, velo mokminan bitrei tannaei tenai ubechada
ta'ama,
rather than saying that it's all the same case and but it's
a debate of תנאים tana'im how to parse his words. So the
גמרא Gemara sees that you know the only way the רישא reisha
can be explained is if it means on the condition you're silent.
The only way the סיפא seifa can be explained is if it
means on the condition you don't object. So do we say that
it's all he said the same words, ירצה אבא, yirtze abba, and
there's a debate of תנאים tana'im how to parse that? Do you
parse it to mean silent or do you parse it to mean
not object? Or do we say no it's actually different circumstances in
one case you said silent and in the other case you said
not object. And he'd rather have it be different circumstances than be
a debate that is where you know a hidden debate going on
here. רב יוסף בר אמי אמר לעולם חדא טעמא הוא, Rav Yosef
Bar Ami Amar Le'olam chada ta'ama hu, really it's all one scenario.
Okay. ומי אמר על מנת שירצה אבא, Umai amar al menat sheyirtze
abba, על מנת שלא ימחה אבא מכאן ועד שלשים יום. al menat
shelo yimche abba mikan ve'ad shloshim yom.
And here finally we get the we get the time limit. Like
it cannot be indefinite. So basically he says is on the condition
that Dad doesn't object for the next thirty days. So the רישא
reisha that says מקודשת, mekudeshet, when is she מקודשת? mekudeshet? It's not
enough to say I agree, because if you think it means don't
object, the גמרא Gemara again thinks you could object after you agreed.
But when is she מקודשת? mekudeshet? When the time limit runs out.
At the end of the thirty days. So the רישא reisha says
she's married is that he didn't object for thirty days and then
the clock ran out. Then the middle case says that if the
father dies, so even during the thirty days she's married because let
me tell you he's not going to object by the end of
thirty days. And in the last case he finds out, so there's
a clock running and he's got thirty days and we teach him
to object within those thirty days. All right, that was very complicated.
Let's go on. Okay. דדחקינן, Dachtinan, they'd rather they'd rather have.
They'd rather avoid a מחלוקת machloket between two different תנאים. Tannaim.
No, not between two different תנאים. Tannaim. They'd rather avoid saying that
an anonymous משנה Mishna that all seems to be one opinion is
really two separate opinions that have not been articulated.
Sometimes they're forced to do that.
Right. Okay, let's look at the next משנה. Mishna. קידשתי את בתי
ואיני יודע למי קידשתיה. Kidashti et biti ve'eini yodeia lemi kidashtiya. אוי.
Oi.
So now we're moving away from the act of קידושין Kiddushin to
the question of נאמנות. ne'emanut. And what's implicit in this משנה, Mishna,
that's even implicit in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell
it out explicitly, is that a father is believed to say that
he married off his daughter. Now funny, because the קידושין Kiddushin doesn't
take place without witnesses. So you could say if you're claiming that
you married your daughter, produce the witnesses. And if you can't produce
the witnesses, we're not going to believe you, right? But nevertheless, the
גמרא Gemara says, based on the פסוק pasuk of where the father
says את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה, et biti natati la'ish hazeh, you
know those פסוקים psukim there about that whole case where he claims
she's not a virgin, you know, and brings out the cloth or
whatever, right? So he says I gave my daughter to this man.
The גמרא Gemara learns from this that a father is believed to
say that he married off his daughter even if he can't produce
any witnesses. So let's say he says he married off his daughter
but he doesn't remember who he married her to. Okay, so now
she's stuck. Like, she can't marry another guy because it might be
adultery. What's she supposed to do, right, remain an עגונה agunah her
whole life? So the
גמרא Gemara says ובא אחד ואמר אני קידשתיה. uva echad ve'amar ani
kidashtiya.
So a man shows up and says oh, I was the guy.
נאמן. ne'eman. He's believed. Okay, which makes life easy. Now he can
give her a גט get or they can choose to be married.
זה אמר אני קידשתיה וזה אמר אני קידשתיה. zeh amar ani kidashtiya
vezeh amar ani kidashtiya. Two people claim they were the ones who
married her, and presumably the father doesn't know, can't discern between them.
שניהם נותנים גט. shneihem notnim get. They both give a גט get
because they both can't be married to her, obviously, and one of
them would be adultery, so he has to get a גט. get.
ואם רצו אחד נותן גט ואחד כונס. ve'im ratzu echad noten get
ve'echad kones.
One can give a גט get and the other can marry, because
ממה נפשך. mimah nafshach. If the guy who married her was the
guy who married her, the guy who's going to stay with her
is the guy who married her, then you don't need a גט
get from the second guy. If the second guy was the guy
who married her, then at least she's now divorced from him and
now she's married to this other guy. Okay, but anyway, so there's
two implicit חידושים chidushim in the משנה, Mishna, one is that you
believe the father, and the other is once you're believing the father,
you're then also prepared to believe a guy who claims it. Why
should we believe a random guy who says it? Right? I mean
the תורה Torah didn't give a random guy any special נאמנות, ne'emanut,
it gave the father special נאמנות. ne'emanut. So let's take a look.
אמר רב. amar Rav. נאמן ליתן גט ואינו נאמן לכנוס. ne'eman liten
get ve'eino ne'eman liknos.
Let's say there's only one guy, and it says the one guy
shows up and says it was me, and it says we believe
him. So he says we only believe him to give a גט,
get, and now she's free to marry somebody else. That's pretty heavy
stuff, because basically now she's, there's no concern of adultery, she's free
to marry. But he's not believed to marry her. What's the difference?
We're going to allow her to marry somebody else, why isn't he
believed to marry her? So the גמרא Gemara says אין אדם חוטא
ולא לו. ein adam chotei velo lo. Okay? נאמן ליתן גט אין
אדם חוטא ולא לו. ne'eman liten get ein adam chotei velo lo.
He's believed to give her a גט get because he won't sin
if he's not going to benefit from it. Meaning if he's here
and lying, what does he have to gain? We're not, actually because
we don't let him marry her, the only person that can gain
from this is some other man who's going to marry her. So
ah, maybe it's adultery and he's lying and he's now going to
allow her to commit adultery with another, he has nothing to gain
from it. So that actually helps us believe him, okay? Because we're
not going to let him marry her.
Okay? ואינו נאמן לכנוס. ve'eino ne'eman liknos. But he can't marry her,
even though you could say well he wouldn't be going ahead and
committing adultery if he wasn't really the man. No. שמא יצרו תקפו.
shema yitzro takpo. If you have a vested interest, your יצר הרע
yeitzer hara gets the better of you, sometimes people do lie and
sin, even with very serious sins. Okay, so if he's going to
gain from the testimony, we don't believe him. Once we prevent him
from any personal benefit, then he's believed דווקא davka for other people.
Yes.
Can't you think of an example, I'm sure there are counterexamples of
situations
where people do things out of
spite?
Right. So especially like cases about the mother-in-law and the sister-in-law and
all of those, we didn't believe people because we were afraid it
was out of spite. So you're saying I guess that's true. Meaning
if it was a case like that where there was a basis
to think he was trying to mess her up. Right. But we
do have cases like that, but usually it's with like the female
relatives in these types of scenarios. But it could be. There's also
cases where people say here's a hundred bucks, go and testify, right?
Anyway, but that's Rav's position.
ולא לו. velo lo. Right. There is no לו.
lo. Right, because you're because you know, maybe somebody is maybe he's
being paid to do it. Right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
now that's רב, Rav, which is a very reasonable position. רב אשי
אמר אף נאמן לכנוס. Rav Ashi amar af ne'eman liknos. No, he
can even marry her, basically because as we're going to see, א,
alef, it would be a big sin for him, and ב, bet,
if he's going to say it's me, he's afraid that the father's
going to say look, I don't know who I married her to
but I know it wasn't you. Like, you know, you're six feet
tall and I know the guy was five-four. So clearly you're lying.
So he doesn't, right? So you don't know if you're going to
be called out on it when you present yourself and say it
was me. So therefore you're believed even for that purpose because you
are, because you would not lie. You don't want to be called
out. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ומודי רב אסי umodei Rav
Assi באומר נתקדשתי ואיני יודעת למי נתקדשתי. be'omer nitkadashti ve'eini yoda'at lemi
nitkadashti. If a woman says, I got married and I don't know
who I married, okay, not the father, she says it about herself.
ובא אחד ואמר קידשתיך, uva echad ve'amar kidashtich, I married her, שאינו
נאמן לכנוס, she'eino neman lichnus, that he's not believed. Now this I,
it's very bizarre. The גמרא's Gemara going to say the reason. Let's
read it in the גמרא Gemara and see the reason, because I
gotta tell you, I don't understand what the גמרא's Gemara reason for
it. תנא, tana, let's keep on going, we'll see about that in
a minute. רצו, ratzu, if the משנה Mishnah says if they want,
אחד נותן גט ואחד כונס. echad noten get ve'echad kones. One gives
a גט get and one can marry. So תיובתא דרב, tiuvta deRav,
it's a contradiction to רב. Rav. רב Rav said that the guy
who says it was me is not believed to marry, and we
see at least in the case of the משנה Mishnah of two
guys that they want, he's believed to marry. So גמרא Gemara says
no. אמר לך רב, amar lach Rav, רב Rav will say to
you,
שאני התם דכיון דאיכא אחרינא בהדיה מרתת. shani hatam dekivan de'ika achrina
bahadei mirtat. Since there's another guy with him, he's afraid to lie.
Like you know, if I'm going to go, there's another guy and
so he assumes that everybody is coming at the same time and
knows what's happening. But anyway, and I'm going to go and there's
another guy there, unless I really believe I'm telling the truth, right?
I'm really afraid because maybe I'm going to get called out as
a liar. The other guy's going to contradict me. The father's going
to recognize the other guy as the guy that did it. So
if I'm the only guy who turns up, maybe I'm not so
afraid, but if there's another guy turning up and he's like looking
at the two of us, like you know, then maybe I'd be
more afraid to lie. Of course, the problem is is that then
you would say that both of them are telling the truth, but
obviously one of them is lying, right? So the way רש"י Rashi
and תוספות, Tosafot, so why all of a sudden do we believe
this guy if now we know that one of you is lying?
So what רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say, it's sort of like
a שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech solution, right? Of okay, but the one
who chose to be the one to give the גט, get, we're
going to presume most likely he's the one who's lying, and the
one who's prepared to go ahead and marry her, I don't know,
it's still a real question why we play it out that way.
Anyway, fine. That's how he deals with the end of the משנה.
Mishnah. תניא כוותיה דרב אסי. tanya kavatei deRav Assi. We taught like
רב אסי. Rav Assi. קידשתי את בתי ואיני יודע למי קידשתי. kidashti
et biti ve'eini yodei lemi kidashti. I don't know who I married
her to. ובא אחד ואמר קידשתיך, uva echad ve'amar kidashtich, אף נאמן
לכנוס. aph neman lichnus. The ברייתא braita explicitly says he's believed to
marry her. כנסה ובא אחר ואמר אני קידשתיך. knesah uva acher ve'amar
ani kidashtich.
Now let's say after he married her, guy number two showed up.
In that case, לא כל הימנו לאוסרה עליו. lo kol heimenu le'osrah
alav. Once now that we have an established, you know, reality that
they're married, we don't start worrying, ah, guy number two. Well, he
should be just as believed as guy number one, and now maybe,
you know, she's an אשת איש eishes ish and she's not married
to guy. No. Once you've established a new reality, like if guy
one testified and hadn't acted on it and guy number two showed
up, that would be a different story. Then one of them would
have to give her a גט. get. But after you've created a
new reality, this guy is not believed to change that reality. Okay,
where were we? המציאות
היא hametziut hi really אחרי שכנסה. acharei sheknesah.
Yeah, exactly.
Now, היא ששאמרה נתקדשתי ואיני יודעת למי נתקדשתי. hi she'amrah nitkadashti ve'eini
yoda'at lemi nitkadashti. Now this was the case where רב אסי Rav
Assi would agree to. The woman said, I got married to a
guy and I don't know who. ובא אחד ואמר אני קידשתיך, uva
echad ve'amar ani kidashtich,
I married you. אינו נאמן לכנוס. eino neman lichnus. He can't. Why?
And here's the reason and you tell me if you understand this
reason. מפני שהיא מחפה עליו. mipnei shehi mechapa alav.
She'll be willing to cover up for him. Now what's the, I
don't understand. רש"י Rashi doesn't explain. You can tell me as your
English or you can figure this out, explains. If the, it says
the father, it's assumed that if I know you're lying, okay,
the guy has to be concerned that he might be seen as
a, he might be called out as a liar. So part of
the reason he's believed is because we assume he wouldn't want to
get called out as a liar. So the assumption is like this:
if I'm going to go ahead and lie and come to the
father, he's going to call me out and the father won't be
מחפה עליו, mechapa alav, he won't try to protect me. But if
I go and I go to this woman who says she married
a guy and she sees that I'm a liar, she sees I'm
not the guy, she'll still at least try to be protective of
me. Why would the woman try more to protect him than the
father? Now you could say because it's in the woman's best interest,
right? As long as nobody shows up, she can't be married to
anyone, because she might be an אשת איש, eishes ish, right? Or
she is an אשת איש eishes ish to somebody. So the woman
has a vested interest to, you know, to believe, even if she
knows he's lying, to play along with any guy who shows up
because it all, because otherwise she's an אשת איש. eishes ish. But
the father also has that interest, he doesn't want his daughter to
be an אשת איש. eishes ish. So presumably what we're saying is
that because, you know, the father, you know, if it's not you
personally, even if it's your daughter, you know, you're going to be
able to be a little bit more honest about it. Okay, yes,
I know my daughter's now going to be an אשת איש eishet
ish for her entire life or whatever, but I know this guy
isn't the guy, and I'm not going to let him give her
a גט get and let her marry some other guy and I
know she'll be an אשת איש. eishet ish. So the father will
call out the liar. But the woman herself, who really is going
to be in this tragic situation, you know, she might more feel
be willing to go along even if she knows it's a lie
because it will free her from her current situation. That presumably is
the difference.
Oh, so
because of her vested interest that she's going to convince herself that
this is the guy. That could be.
Right, right, vested interest in not being an עגונה. agunah.
Right, which is more, which is true for the father in terms
of his daughter, but it's more powerful for the woman herself. So
right, maybe you're right, maybe it's not exactly a lie, but allow
themselves to believe that this is the guy.
Right, memory is right, exactly, yes.
By the principle that the mouth that prohibits is the mouth to
permit, couldn't she simply say after the guy shows up, 'Oh, now
I remember that this is the guy'?
Well, yes, if she says it, she would be believed, but all
the cases thus far say are not saying it, that we're trusting
the guy, not the original person. Okay, to be continued.